<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A lytle treatise after the maner of an epystle wryten by the famous clerk Doctor Vrbanus Regius, vnto a specyall frynde of hys wherin he declareth the cause of the great co[n]trouersy that hath bene [and] is yet at this day in the chrysten relygyon and also the dyuersyte betwene the ryght worshyppyng [and] seruice of God and the ceremonis inuented by mannis institucion, very fruteful and profytable.</title>
            <author>Rhegius, Urbanus, 1489-1541.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1548</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 63 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 28 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10579</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20849</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S115824</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99851042</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99851042</idno>
            <idno type="VID">16295</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10579)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 16295)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 142:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A lytle treatise after the maner of an epystle wryten by the famous clerk Doctor Vrbanus Regius, vnto a specyall frynde of hys wherin he declareth the cause of the great co[n]trouersy that hath bene [and] is yet at this day in the chrysten relygyon and also the dyuersyte betwene the ryght worshyppyng [and] seruice of God and the ceremonis inuented by mannis institucion, very fruteful and profytable.</title>
                  <author>Rhegius, Urbanus, 1489-1541.</author>
                  <author>Holbein, Hans, 1497-1543, artist.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[56] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprinted by me [Steven Mierdman for] Gwalter Lynne, dwellyng vpon Somers kaye, by Byllynges gate,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>In the yeare of our Lorde God. M.D.Xlviij. [1548]]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Original title not found.</note>
                  <note>Actual printer's name from STC; publisher's name and publication date from colophon.</note>
                  <note>With a title-page woodcut signed: Hans Holbein.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-C D⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:16295:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:16295:1"/>
            <p>A lytle treati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe after the maner of an Epyſtle Wryten by the famous clerk Doctor vrba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus Regius, vnto a ſpecyall frynde of hys, wherin he declareth the cauſe of the great co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſy that hath bene &amp; is yet at this day in the chryſten relygyon and alſo the dyuer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſyte betwene the ryght worſhyppyng &amp; ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice of God and the ceremonis inuented by mannis inſtitucion, very fruteful and profy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>table.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Iohn .x. Ezech .xxxiiij. Mich .v.</bibl>
               <p>I am the good ſhepehearde. A good ſhepehearde ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth his lyfe for the ſhype.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>scene from John 10:13</figDesc>
                  <signed>HANS HOLBEIN</signed>
               </figure>
               <p>The hyred ſeruaunt flyeth, becauſe he is an hered ſeruaunt and careth not for the ſhepe.</p>
            </q>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:16295:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:16295:2"/>
            <head>The Epiſtell of doctor Vrbanus Regius.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is no maruaile that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny good vertuous perſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes at this tyme are trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled wythin them ſelues not knowinge howe to or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der them ſelues for to come to goodnes, becauſe that there are ſo fewe faythfull ſhepeheardes and Preachers, that can teache the ryght waye to ryghteouſnes and ſaluacion, and in the meane whyle men crye on both ſydes, that men do er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re greuouſly. By the reaſon wherof the poore ſymple man knoweth not, whiche ſyde he may take, and which he ought to forſake wherfore I wyll here exhybyte my poore ſeruice vnto youre wyſdome, &amp; by the grace of God geue you a ſhorte inſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, howe the matter of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten relygyon at this tyme ſtandeth.</p>
            <p>Fyrſt is to be noted, that in the chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che from the Apoſtles tyme, vnto thys daye, it ſtode neuer ſo well in the church, that there was no parcyalyte and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſie for the doctrynes ſake. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore nowe to be brefe, all varyaunce and
<pb facs="tcp:16295:3"/>
controuerſie ryſeth vpon this queſtion, howe men ſhall be made righteous, and which is the ryght waye to God?</p>
            <p>Secondely, here hath been alwayes controuerſye and variaunce, yea euen in the Apoſtles dayes,<note place="margin">Actu. 15.</note> as ye maye reade. The one wyll be made ryghteous and quite from ſynne, and obtayne a mercy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full God by this maner, the other by y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> maner, wherfore it can not be denyed but that the one muſt nedes erre, here ry<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſeth then variaunce and controuerſye, for the wicked enemie, is an enemy to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> true doctryne, and to the catolyke fayth, becauſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> men through y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> true doctryne &amp; fayth are made ryghteous, and by the ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me eſcape from the power of the wicked enemy, and are ſaued. Therfore doth he rayſe &amp; ſtyrre vp errours, for to ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten his kingedome.</p>
            <p>Thyrdely, here haue alwayes ben two partes, the one parte hath ſought to be iuſtyfyed and ſaued by certayne meanes, which coulde not helpe them to ryghteouſnes, as the Iewes, which wol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de be ſaued and delyuered from their ſin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes by the corporall circunciſion. The Saracenes (which now are the Turkes)
<pb facs="tcp:16295:3"/>
truſt to be ſaued and iuſtifyed, by the ke<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pinge of their Alkaron, and doynge of outwarde workes: And alwayes who ſoeuer ordereth hym ſelfe in this matter after the iudgement of his wyttes, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth ſome workes before hym, by the which he thinketh to amende his ſinnes, to make ſatiſfaction vnto God for his ſynnes, to obtaine grace, &amp; (to be ſhort) to be iuſtyfyed and ſaued, as all they do nowe alſo that wyll meryte and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue heauen at the handes of God, by mans inſtitucio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, &amp; their owne workes.</p>
            <p>For they thinke, whan the lawe is de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>clared vnto them, what they muſt do &amp; leaue vndone, that it is ſuffycient, and that as than theyr wyttes maye know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge the ſame for a good and perfect doctrine (for they knowe that men muſt be ryghteous) &amp; that then y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wyll of men maye yelde hym ſelfe there in, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſente to fulfyll the ſame wyth the dedes. And whan a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nowe throug his wyt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes and vnderſtandinge knoweth that which is good, and the wylle geuet him ſelfe ouer therin to perfourme the ſame, that than he obtaineth grace and fauour before God, and is conuerted and made
<pb facs="tcp:16295:4"/>
ryghteous.</p>
            <p>But this opynyon is wicked and fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe, and this is the princypall cauſe of the ſtryfe and controuerſye in theſe dayes, and they that haue the holy gooſt haue euer reſyſted the ſame, and confuted this errour, for this is not the ryght waye to ryghteouſnes and ſaluacion.</p>
            <p>The true ryghteouſnes is farre other<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wyſe then that ſhe ſo eaſely ſhoulde be executed onely by a ſynful mannes wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te. For yf ſhe ſhoulde after that ſorte be obtayned, then ſhuld man neede no more iuſtificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but a good ordinaunce, for yf he hadde the ſame, he myght be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of his owne ſtrenght to be obedient to the ſame: Truly then hadde it ben ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fycyent, that God had ſent Moſes vpon earth, to teache vs, what we ſhoulde do or leaue vndone, and than we myght ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e done it, and ſo we ſhoulde haue ben <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>ſtifyed and ſaued. But where ſhoulde Chriſte become then? Nowe myghte a Chriſten man thinke ones, wherfore did God him ſelfe become man? Why was Chriſte ſent downe from heauen? wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore dyed he?<note place="margin">Rom. 6.</note> why are we baptiſed in his death, and named after him, that we are
<pb facs="tcp:16295:4"/>
Chriſten men after Chriſte our Lorde? Sure it is, that ſuch a great thinge is not done in vayne, God truely had no nede of vs he coulde haue forborne oure man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hode well ynough, our manhode verely made hym not God, nor added any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection vnto hym which he had not befo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re, why are we not called Moſini after Moyſes? Is it not to be lamented y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we are ſo blinde and negligent in his godly matters? that we haue not at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> leaſt ones thought wherfore God cauſed his ſonne to become man to ſuffre to dye, to ryſe agayne from death? why he ſuffered ſuch a vylanous death vpon the croſſe, &amp; roſe againe, &amp; aſcended into heauen? Is all this the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in vaine? But if it be ſome great matter let any man tell me wherfore it was done and what Chriſte did meane and execute by the ſame? Many ſymple perſons thinke y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> this preſent controuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerninge our beleue &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Chriſten re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lygion is onely a wylfull preſumption, and that men might contente the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues well ynough and leaue the churche in relte, and that there is no nede of ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che controuerſye, and that the churche
<pb facs="tcp:16295:5"/>
is in caſe good ynough. They ſuppoſe alſo, that this ſtryfe and varyaunce is onely ryſen becauſe of the cerymony<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, and that there is no faute nor er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour in any other pointes, wherfore me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> myght contente the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues wel ynough.</p>
            <p>To this do I anſwere, that they are foull deceyued, and erre greuouſly. For there is another maner of matter in the waye, and there be farre greater occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of this controuerſye than onely the ceremonies: We woulde not ones take a penne in hande, or make one ſermon, onely forſome ſeremonies ſake. Alas o God, thys ſtryfe is for Chryſtes ſake, Hym will not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worlde yet knowe, She wyll come vnto God without hym, not wythſtandinge that there is none other waye to God,<note place="margin">Ioh. 14.</note> but by Chriſte.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Iohn. 1.</note> The worlde nameth Chriſte, but ſhe knoweth hym not, for ſhe deſpyſeth the Goſpel which teatcheth Chriſte, the true ſaluacion. Men ſtryfe for it, which is the ryghtwaye to God, and we teache that it is Chriſte. And that no mannes wyſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome nor vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dinge, can of her ſelfe fynde oute, knowe or ſhewe this waye to euerlaſting lyfe, nor be made ryghteous
<pb facs="tcp:16295:5"/>
through any maner of natural ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the, but that God hym ſelfe muſt teache vs the ryght waye to God by the holy gooſt in his worde, and that he him ſelfe muſt make vs good or righteous, which is done onely by the faith in Chriſte. Shulde mans witte it ſelfe knowe, what is ſynne, what true righteouſnes, and whiche is the true waye to the kingdom of God, or yf man by his owne wyſedo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhulde knowe the true goddes ſeruyce, than myght alſo Plato. Ariſtotel, Cice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro, Plinie, and other heathen of hyghe &amp; excellent wittes haue attayned be rygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes and ſaluacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Wherin did they fayle than, or what dyd they lacke? Anſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>were, they were but naturall men, and they had no goſpell. But the nature of man, was in Adam ſo myſerably cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted and blynded through ſynne, that euen in naturall thinges ſhe hath no ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re knowledge, howe ſhulde ſhe then at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne to the knowledge of ſpirituall and eternall thinges? As for an example, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſtotel knewe none other, but that the wytte and diſcretion of man is ſuche a perfect lyghte, which in euerye point is to be followed, as that whiche teacheth
<pb facs="tcp:16295:6"/>
the thynge whiche is ryghte and iuſte, and leadeth to the beſte. And that anger and ire is not ſo great a ſynne, but a wet ſtone of quickenes and fearcenes, and that it is not to be blamed what ſoeuer is in vs of nature, as though oure natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re were vncorrupte and vngylty. Item that the wytte and dyſcretyon of man, may rule and mayſtre, wrath, enuye, immodeſtye, puſyllanymitie, ryghte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes, vnryghteouſnes, and other ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke motions of the ſoule, and that by this rulynge and mayſterynge he maye pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare hym ſelfe to all vertues, ſo that a man thorough his owne wytte maye become meke or gentle towardes men, in all thynges meaſurable, ſtrong her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted or magnanyme in all aduerſytye, and geue to euery man y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which is right and iuſt. Plyuye was of this opynyon, that the ſoule dyed wyth the body for if the ſoules ſhoulde yet all lyue (ſayth he) where ſhoulde ſo many ſoules haue rowme in the worlde?<note place="margin">Epicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians.</note> The Epicurians and their adherentes ſuppoſed that God medleth not w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the world, and y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hecareth not what is done here beneth whether it be good or euell, but that he ſuffereth
<pb facs="tcp:16295:6"/>
all thinges to go after their inclinatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s.<note place="margin">Actu. 17.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The learned and ingenious heathen at Athenes in Grece toke S. Paules doc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trine of the reſurrection, for a fantaſty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call dreame. Plinius the elder, calleth the doctrin of the immortalytye of bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and ſoule, bablinge of chyldren. Pli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius the yonger, and Suetonius cal our holy catholyke faith,<note place="margin">Iohn. 3.</note> a newe ſorcerous ſuperſticion. What knewe Nicodeme (a hygh learneth Pharyſee amonge the Ie<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wes) of the regeneracion? To be brefe, the witte of man with his lyghte, and the doctryne of Chriſte,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 1.</note> are ſo farre vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyke, that Paule (i. Cor. i.) ſayeth. That the wiſdome of man, iudgeth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Goſpell to be foolyſhneſſe. Nowe, the aboue na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med wiſe men haue ſtudied and ſought with all their powers, to knowe highe thinges of God &amp; of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but what heue they gotten? Is not their ſainges great blindenes? It may be felt ryght well, that nature doth neither vnderſto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de nor yet conclude in the harte, any truth or fu+/enes in godly matters, She waxeth y<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle and vayne in her ymaginacions, and her vndiſcrete harte is darkened. Whan ſhe counteth her ſelfe wiſe, ſhe becometh foliſſhe, as Paule ſayeth. Rom. i. What
<pb facs="tcp:16295:7"/>
nede many wordes? ſeinge the ſcrypture ſpeakinge of Adams ſonne, affyrmeth that he laith in herte,<note place="margin">Pſa. 14. Ephe. 2. Rom. 15 1. Teſ. 4. Rom. 1.</note> there is no God. And Paul ſayth, the heathen (that is all they that haue not the worde of God &amp; the fayth in chriſte) are wythout God in this worlde. And ſayth he they kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we not God. This is ſure, that nature is ſo blynde without Goddes worde, that ſhe ſuffreth her ſelfe to be treatened, that God wyll puniſſhe ſynne, but ſhe doth deſpyſe it and doth not beleue it. She can ſuffre many good thinges to be promy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed vnto her, but ſhe carreth not for it &amp; ſhe regardeth not God,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 2.</note> ſhe taketh it for fables, as Paul ſaith, the naturall man (that is, he that doth not yet truelye be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue in Chriſte) perceaueth not thoſe thin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges that belonge to the ſpirite of God for it is fooliſhneſſe vnto him, and he can not vnderſtande it: for it muſt be examy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned ſpyrytually.</p>
            <p>Foraſmuche nowe as the wyſedome of man, before he is regenerate, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leuing in Chriſte, becauſe of his naturall blyndenes and vntowardnes, knoweth not God, feareth him not, regardeth him not loketh for no goodnes at his hande,
<pb facs="tcp:16295:7"/>
nor yet careth for him,<note place="margin">Marke well.</note> howe ſhulde the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a man by his owne wyſdome wyll or poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſybilitie, or through all the power and ſtrenght that he hath fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his fyrſt birth be able to come vnto God, to knowledge hys ſynnes, to haue repentaunce, to ſer, ue God truly, and to become righteous? Therfore maye well the wyſedome of man imagyne many wayes for to quen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che ſynne, and to obtayne righteouſnes, But they are all Erronious by pathes, which leade from God, to wardes hel, &amp; do onely couer y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſinnes before y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worlde, But it is leſſe then nothinge auayllable before God, for it is mery blindnes and hypocryſye, which is enemy to God, as both the olde and the newe Teſtamente declare in euery corner.</p>
            <p>Thus is nowe this a true ſayenge, whithout anye contradiction, that man in godly matters pertayning to ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (as howe a man maye be delyuered fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſinne, and obtaine mercy, ſerue God, be iuſtifyed and ſaued) by his natural light of vnderſtandinge is able to do nothing that is good, but is ſtarcke blynde, and he muſt haue a greater lyght from abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue, namely the holy gooſt, he it is that
<pb facs="tcp:16295:8"/>
muſte illumin the harte with the Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten fayth, loue, hope, and ſuch lyke gif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of God, which Chriſte the ſonne of God hath deſerued for vs.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 10</note>The holy gooſt commeth by the prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chinge of the Goſpell, which Goſpel tea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cheth howe a man ſhal be made ryghte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, ſerue God truly, and obtaine ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.<note place="margin">Marke well.</note> Wherfore we muſt turne our eyes to the goſpell, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we may learne of God him ſelfe, howe we ſhall ſerue him in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynes. Thou arte a man, &amp; yet canſt not ſuffre, that thy ſeruaunt ſhoulde ſerue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> after his owne minde and braine howe ſhal than God ſuffre of vs, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> euery man wyll ſerue hym after his owne blynde good intencion?<note place="margin">Iohn. 3. Rom. 5. 1. Ioh. 4. Math. 9 15. Luc. 19. Ioh. 12. 1. tim. 1, 2</note> For he hath ſent Chriſte for this purpoſe, that he ſhulde preache the goſpell, and declare the wyll of hys father, vnto the worlde, to thintent that we myght learne, what GOD inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth towardes vs, what ſynne is, what vertue and ryghteouſnes is, and howe we ſhall be made good &amp; ryghteous, for to ſerue God truely, &amp; to come vnto him.</p>
            <p>Yf our wiſdom it ſelfe knewe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> right way of truth, and were wyſe ynough of her ſelf in godly matters, to what ende
<pb facs="tcp:16295:8"/>
then ſhulde God haue ſent Chriſte, &amp; the Apoſtles? What nede ſhuld we haue of the holy ſcriptures? Naye whoſoeuer wyll neyther fayle nor erre, muſt nedes loke on Goddes worde, euen there &amp; no where elles ſhall he fynde the right tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the and the ryght waye.</p>
            <p>We reade that Chriſt is the lyght,<note place="margin">Iohn. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> to illumyne the worlde, wherof it muſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des followe that ſhe is darke &amp; ignorau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in godly matters. And Iohn .xiiij.<note place="margin">Ioh. 14.</note> ſayth Chriſt, I am the waye the truthe and the lyfe, no man cometh vnto the father but by me. But what maner of light &amp; waye he is, and howe a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may obtayne hym for his owne muſt be learned onely out of the goſpell. And Paule ſaith .ij.<note place="margin">2. Tim. 3</note> Tim. iij. That the ſcripture is able to inſtructe vs, vnto ſaluation. Is not this cleare &amp; plain ynough y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> whoſoeuer wil knowe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> truthe how he ſhal be ſaued muſt learne it out of the ſcrypture? He ſaith not that he ſhall folowe hys owne mynde and good intencion.</p>
            <p>Moreouer Moiſes writeth. Deu. xij.<note place="margin">Deu. 12.</note> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> noma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhall do what ſemeth hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> good whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che is as much to ſay, he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> will do well, be good &amp; righteous, &amp; ſerue God, muſt
<pb facs="tcp:16295:9"/>
learne it of God, in his worde, and not of his owne wyſdome, or of menne. And Chriſt ſayth,<note place="margin">Mat. 15</note> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> God is worſhypped in vayne wyth mennes preceptes, this is ſpoken playne ynough. Yf ye will ſerue God truely, than do it not wyth men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes tradicions, for it is in vayne, But do it accordinge to the worde of God, and than can ye not erre nor do amyſſe.</p>
            <p>For aſmuche nowe as no man by his owne inuented wayes mannes inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, can truely ſerue God, be delyue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red from his ſynnes, and be made righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, but muſte before all thinges ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue Chriſte to the ſame: We wyll ſhewe and declare howe and after what ſorte the ſame is done, whereby euerye man ſhal eaſely perceiue, what an Erronious doctryne hath ben preached a great why<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>le in the Chriſtianitie.</p>
            <p>Therfore note, that a man maye be made good and ryghteous after two ſor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes.<note place="margin">Marke well.</note> Firſt before y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worlde, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as a ſcole-maiſter kepeth a boye in awe, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrayneth hym weth the rodde and feare of correction, to walke regularely and to hurte noman, or euen as a magiſtrate correcteth the euyll doers ſo ſtrayghtly, that
<pb facs="tcp:16295:9"/>
y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> many me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> outwardely leade an honeſte lyfe for feare of puniſſheme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, they ſteale not, they kyll nome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, they paye theyr deb<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes, they are not ouerous to their neygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, neyther concernynge his body, wyfe nor chylde, ſo that it may be ſaide, they are good honeſt men, ſuche beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueour and honeſt conuerſacion is good, and God doth alſo require it. Therfore hath he in the worlde ordeyned the ſwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de to the temporall powers,<note place="margin">Sapi. 6. Rom. 13. 1. Petr. 2 Titu. 3. Pro. 20. and. 24.</note> and chaſty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſement of children, to thintent that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple maye leade an honeſt, good and ſtil lyfe, not after their owne luſtes, but that they maye be compelled ſo to walke, that the neighbour maye perceyue it, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> good peace and outwardely and honeſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſacion maye continue amonge men.</p>
            <p>But yet this is nothynge elles but worke holynes, cyuyle policye, and wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dely ryghteouſnes, whiche alſo may be founde well ynough amonge the infy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delles, which through the lawe of natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, in their opinion iudge it good &amp; righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, that a man leade an honeneſt lyfe and conuerſacion, committe none adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery, do no murther, ſteale not, lye not, and deceaue no man. &amp;c.</p>
            <gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:16295:10"/>to ſaye) for there is no thefe hanged for his thoughtes becauſe he mindeth or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendeth to ſteale, as longe as he doth not accomplyſſhe the dede. But all this is not ſuffycient before God: for he ſeeth in the harte, and wyll that men ſhall beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue them ſelues godly in truthe and from the botome of the harte, ſo that the harte mouth and ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de be good &amp; ryghteous. When is that done? Whan ye haue a luſte in youre harte, to be honeſte, ſober, chaſte, frendlye towardes all men.</p>
            <p>And whan ye haue a lothſomnes and prkeſomnes to euil, as dronkenes, vnclen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lynes, thefte, maliciouſnes, murther and ſuche lyke. But this is nature not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to do of her ſelfe,<note place="margin">Iob. 4.15.25. Pſa. 14.53. &amp;. 143 Rom. 3. Pſal. 51.</note> becauſe that the luſt of euyll cleaueth ſo faſt vnto vs fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our original natiuite, &amp; powred into our na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture through y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fyrſte ſynne, in ſo moch y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ſcripture doth openly call vs euill &amp; peruerſe euen from our mothers wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>be.</p>
            <p>Therfore muſt the harte fyrſt be clen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed from ſuch vnclenlynes, &amp; gette pure thoughtes, luſtes and affections, &amp; after<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wardes may a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> do right good workes &amp; than is a man made right good &amp; righ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teous both inwardely and outwardely.</p>
            <p>Nowe teacheth the ſcrypture that our
<pb facs="tcp:16295:10"/>
hart is purifyed by none other thynge, but by the true faith in Chriſte Actu. xv. Faith commeth by the workinge and il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luminatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the holy gooſt,<note place="margin">Actu. 15.</note> by the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rynge of the goſpell. Rom. x.<note place="margin">Rom. 10</note> Wherfor he that wyll truely be made righteous, muſt purely and ſyncerely heare and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue the goſpell of Chriſte, or elles he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinueth a natural man without grace.</p>
            <p>What is the goſpell?<note place="margin">Marke well.</note> It is a predica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Chriſte, what he is, and what he doth,<note place="margin">Math. 9 and .15. Luc. 19. Ioh. 3.12 Roma. 5 1. tim. 1.2 1. Ioh. 4 Gene. 2. Rom. 6. and .5.</note> as that he was ſent from the father of mere loue and fauoure, to helpe the ſynner. But howe doth he helpe? The ſynner ſtycketh faſte in ſynne, which he can not amende or put out him ſelfe, he ſtycketh in death, for death is the rewar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de of ſynne. Whoſoeuer committeth ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, hath after the righteous iudgement of God deſerued to dye both temporal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and perpetually, and to be the deuils owne vnto damnacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, out of which cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuitie noman is able to eſcape by hys owne power or ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ght. Man is in ſuch myſerable and pyteous caſe, becauſe of his fyrſt birth of Adam,<note place="margin">1 Co. 15.</note> that he is a ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner borne, condemned to death and dam<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nation, captiue vnder the power of the
<pb facs="tcp:16295:11"/>
deuyll, in the kingdome of darkenes w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> body and ſoule to euerlaſtinge payne. Nowe yf there ſhulde come a man, and paye for the ſinne (which is deathes ſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge) and make vs cleane &amp; ryghteous, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroye y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fearfull death, &amp; make that we myght lyue for euer in body and ſoule, &amp; ouercome the deuill, &amp; make vs fre from his power, ſo that neyther ſynne, deuyll nor death might hurte vs animore, were not this well holpen? Nowe are not we able to do the ſame, neyther any angell, but onely God can do it, &amp; wyll alſo do it, wherfore he hath ſent his onely begot<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ten ſonne, to become man euen as we, a very man in all pointes onely ſynne ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepte, which dyed for oure ſynnes, and hath by the onely ſacryfyce of his body vpon the croſſe, and the ſhedinge of his bloude, made amendes for oure ſinnes, made a perfect ſatiſfaction, reconſiled vs to his heauenly father, &amp; deſerued for vs the holy gooſt with his giftes, he roſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deade,<note place="margin">Mat. 23 Mar. 16 Ioh. 20.</note> brought againe lyfe and declared y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame vnto vs, &amp; alſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded the Apoſtles to publiſhe it vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till the laſt daye, to thintent that whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer
<pb facs="tcp:16295:11"/>
beleueth in Chriſte, and truſteth to hym for ſuche a helpe, maye take ſuche a great worke of Chriſte for his owne, &amp; be ryghteous and ſaue.<note place="margin">mat. 3.7 Luce. 3.</note> Therfore is the goſpell ſuch a predication, which exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth euery man to amendement of lyfe, and to ceaſe from ſinnes, which to paye haue coſt Chriſte ſo much that he dyeth for their ſakes: And admoniſheth al men to beleue in Chriſte,<note place="margin">Mat. 11.</note> and to come vnto hym, as to the true ſauiour of the world which onely can and wyll helpe, both te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porally and euerlaſtingly.<note place="margin">Ioh. 14. &amp; .15.16.</note> Onely in his name and for his ſake will God be mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyfull vnto vs, forgeue vs all oure ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and excepte vs for his children, that we maye be the chyldre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of God through the fayth in Chriſte, heyres of God, and fellowe heyres wyth Ieſus Chryſte our ſauiour for euer.</p>
            <p>Whoſoeuer therfore, beleueth the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell of Chriſte,<note place="margin">Mat. 16. Ioh. 6</note> and doubteth not but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Chriſte is the very ſonne of God, both God and man, that he hym ſelfe hath puryfyed vs from all ſynnes,<note place="margin">Eſa. 53.</note> and bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ught vs from euerlaſtinge death, wyht his precious bloude, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we lyue through
<pb facs="tcp:16295:12"/>
Chriſte in euerlaſting ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, is made righteous &amp; good. For this will y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcryp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, that the faith in Chriſt is oure righ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teouſnes before God,<note place="margin">Rom. 4. Galat. 3</note> whan we truſte to obtayne remyſſyon of our ſynnes and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lyfe euerlaſtynge not by oure dedes or deſeruinges, but onely throug the mere mercy and grace of God, and the infy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyte merytes and great myghtye wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes of Chiſte.</p>
            <p>Wher as ſuche a fayth is, there fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth a right chriſten lyfe, and ryght good workes, Howe be it this faith is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worke of the holy gooſt, he muſt ſo illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine our harte, that fyrſt it may know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge his greate and many folde ſynnes aright, for the whiche we haue deſerued euerlaſtinge damnation. Here muſt we conſyder the intollerable earneſt of the wrath of God ouer ſynne, which he ſo hateth that he wyll not ſuffre it, but pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſſhe it temporally and eternally. And that the ſinne is ſo wicked and greuous, that no man can remedye nor clenſe it, but onely the ſonne of God of heauen hym ſelfe through his owne precious bloude. Than is the harte abaſhed and afrayed euen from the botome, for the
<pb facs="tcp:16295:12"/>
ſtraight iudgement of God, and there is rayſed a ryght and true repentaunce for the ſynnes ſake, after this doth alſo the holy gooſt illumme the humble and broken harte with the knowledge of the infynyte mercy of God, promyſed and geuen through Chriſte, that the harte be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gynneth agayne to receyue conforte, &amp; beleueth ſtedfaſtely, that his ſynnes are nowe all amended an forgeuen hym, through the holſome death of Ieſus Chriſte: And that God from the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cefurth wyll be no more a terryble iudge, but a mercyfull father, for Chiſtes ſake, which hath taken vs to him ſelfe, and hath bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne our iniquities, and made ſatiſfaction for our tranſgreſſyons.<note place="margin">Marke well.</note>
            </p>
            <p>This is the ryght and true Chriſten fayth. The deuils and falſe Chriſtians can alſo reade, heare and remembre y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> paſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſion of Chriſte: But they haue not this lyuely fayth, and this truſt and confy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in God, their harte loketh for no ſuche comforte and grace at Goddes handes. But a Chriſten man is myghte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly comforted of the goſpell, for he doth affyrme it in his harte to be true, and get<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teth ſuch a ſtronge and ioyful confyden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce
<pb facs="tcp:16295:13"/>
in God, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he truſteth to him, as a chil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de to his father, &amp; loketh for all comforte and helpe from God, in all his aduerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyes,<note place="margin">Mat. 7.</note> he doubteth not but that which the Goſpell teacheth, is the euerlaſtinge vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted trueth, and taketh God to be true in all his promyſes, and ſo mighty, wyſe,<note place="margin">Eſa. 49. and .66. Iere. 14.</note> and mercyfull towardes vs, that he hath a reſpect vnto vs, and maketh al thynges good, howe ſo euer it goeth with vs, that he alſo alwayes and euery where hath his eyes vpon vs, that he ke<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>peth, fedeth and defendeth vs, euen as a father loketh to his deare chylde, and for ſaketh it not in any neceſſytye. Bryefly a Chryſten man doth ſurely holde and conclude in his harte, that there is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakeably more conforte, helpe, aſſyſten<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce, faythfulnes, loue, and more goodnes of all thinges by God, wherwith he wil helpe vs, than any man, euer is able to expreſſe, thinke, beleue or hope. There be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>commeth than the herte mery in God, that it loueth God as a father, and ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth frely with a luſt to do good, &amp; pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yeth wyllingely and earneſtly, helpeth his neyghbour, &amp; beco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth an enemye to ſynne. There ſerueth God, &amp; myny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreth
<pb facs="tcp:16295:13"/>
vnto the neyghbour, not onely the hande, the tunge and the fete outwarde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but alſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> harte within y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> body mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth truely without diſſymulation.</p>
            <p>Such a faith and knowledge of God is a high thinge, it ſuffereth not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> man to continue as he was before, but it ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth him pure and vpryght, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he getteth another mynde, other thoughtes and lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes than he had before, he hath a reſpect to the wyll of God in all thinges which he doeth, and endeuoureth hym ſelfe to lyue accordynge to the ſame, with luſte and gladnes, euen as a chylde doth glad<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly and wyth all his harte accomplyſhe the wyll of his father. But a ſeruaunt ſerueth for wages &amp; rewardes, for feare of correction, vnwillingly &amp; lothſomely. for he woulde rather do otherwiſe. Ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>for it procedeth all of an vnwyllinge ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſe harte, what ſoeuer ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doth vnto god w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> out grace. But wherſoeuer is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> grace of faith, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> man ſerueth wyllyngly and gladly in ſpyrite &amp; truth. Therfore doth Chriſt magnifye and anaunce this faith in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goſpel very highly, for it doth great thinges, and bringeth all goodnes. It tourneth the harte towardes GOD
<pb facs="tcp:16295:14"/>
that it may feare God, truſt in him, loue him, and hope in him onely, this is the fyrſt commaundement.</p>
            <p>It ſtyrreth vp the harte, that it doth confydently call to God, prayeth, ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth thankes, laudeth and prayſeth the name of God, and that it vſeth God on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the honor and glory of God, this is the ſeconde commaundement.</p>
            <p>It chaungeth man, that he denieth hym ſelfe, and wholy geueth him ſelfe ouer into the handes of God, and ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth God to rule, and to ordre vs as it pleaſeth hym, ſuffereth God to worke in vs, that we be made a newe creature in Chriſte, and ſtande in a ſtedfaſte and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynuall exercyſe of a godly lyfe, and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue God accordinge to his worde vnder the croſſe in pacience.<note place="margin">Heb. 12. Prou. 3. Apoc. 3.</note> As they that know ryghtwell, that God chaſteneth his ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rely beloued chyldren, that he maye ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke them good, and wyll helpe them wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they call vnto him,<note place="margin">Pſa. 50.</note> accordinge to his pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>myſe, Pſalme .l. Call vnto me in the day of trouble, and I wyll delyuer the, and thou ſhalt prayſe me, this is the thyrde commaundement.</p>
            <p>Where ſoeuer this fayth is, there is
<pb facs="tcp:16295:14"/>
the holy gooſt, which powreth loue in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> harte, loue is the fullfyllynge of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lawe Roma .xiij.<note place="margin">1. Cor. 13. Rom. 13.</note> For loue honoureth father &amp; mother and ſhe is obedient to the hyer po<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wers. This is the fourth commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>Loue kepeth her ſelfe from anger, ſhe is meke and gentyll towardes all men, kylleth not, neyther can beare any maly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce in the harte. In the .v. commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>Loue hath not in her harte to put her neyghbour to diſhoneſtie or wronge concerning wyfe and children,<note place="margin">1. Co. 13.</note> in the .vi. commaundement.</p>
            <p>Loue ſtealeth not, but ſhe geueth and helpeth wher ſoeuer ſhe can and maye, in the .vii. commaundement.</p>
            <p>Loue bereth no falſe witnes, but aſſy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſteth the truthe, ſhe helpeth to ſaue her neyghbours honeſtye, to couer and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fende his faultes, in the .viij. commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement.</p>
            <p>Loue coueteth not her neyghbours goodes wyfe nor chylde, but rather hel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>peth him to kepe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame, in the .ix. and .x. commaundement.</p>
            <p>Thus do we ſee that faith which wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>keth
<pb facs="tcp:16295:15"/>
by loue, is the fountayne of al good workes. Yf the worke ſhal be good than muſt it flowe out of ſuch a faith endued with loue. Faith muſt be there before y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> workes, that it may make y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> perſon faith full and good. Nowe, when y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> perſonne hath faith and loue, then doth he fyrſt good workes and no rather. Do what ſoeuer ye wyll, yf ye haue not this faith, your harte is not cleane, &amp; youre workes are not good. But this faith kepeth the ten co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundementes, for it can ſetman to behaue him ſelfe vpryghtly towardes God and his neighbour.</p>
            <p>Nowe, whan we prayſe and magny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fye this faith, as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> onely true ryghteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes before God, that is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worlde angry and ſuppoſeth that we do it of contempt and contumacye, &amp; can not vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de, that we there with fyrſt of all do teache and ſet vp the true good workes. Whan we teache this faith, becauſe there is no worke good without this faith, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> do we fyrſt plante the tree,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 7.</note> after that do we plante the frute, that is the true natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall ordinaunce. For ſo hath Chriſte done lykewyſe, and the Apoſtles.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Marke well.</note>Nowe are there many thinges in the Chriſtianite for a longe tyme &amp; ſeaſon v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb facs="tcp:16295:15"/>
and taken for good, &amp; for goddes ſer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uice whiche are cleane contrarye to this wholſome doctrine, &amp; to this faith: wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore the ſame are iuſtely reiected and con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>demned. And therfore rageth the worlde and can not vnderſtande, that it is done of a good zeale, &amp; by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> commaundement of God. For y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worlde can not vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de the righteouſnes of God (y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> true faith in Chriſte) &amp; the frutes therof. She vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth onely y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> righteouſnes of wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes, &amp; worſhippinges of god, or goddes ſeruices inue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted by mans owne brayne. Out of this doth cheifely ryſe al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uerſie in the worlde.</p>
            <p>Foraſmuch nowe, as out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goſpell of S,<note place="margin">Iohn. 1. Rom. 4. Gala. 3.</note> Ioh. S. Paules epiſtles to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines, &amp; Galathia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> true grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lawe &amp; the Prophetes, it is cleare &amp; euidently concluded, that there is none other righteouſnes of valour before god than the faith of the Goſpell in Chriſte: And foraſmuche as there is none other waye, to obtaine pardon &amp; remiſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes, to be made good and righteous &amp; to be ſaued, than the ſame faith in Chriſt whiche Chriſte was geuen vs of the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to thyntent, that he onely by hys owne workes ſhoulde make vs good, &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:16295:16"/>
be him ſelfe our euerlaſtinge ryghteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, lyfe and ſaluacion, yf we beleue in him. It followeth then without any contradiction, of the ſame, that in many poyntes, from certaine hondreth yeres vnto this daye, we haue groſſely erred, and that all other meanes and wayes, which haue ben ſet vp for to obtayne by them remyſſyon of ſynnes, and grace, or to be made good and ryghteous, and to obtayne ſaluacion, are nothing elles but Erronious by pathes, and not the true Goddes ſeruice.</p>
            <p>Nowe wyll I in a ſumme recyte the pryncypall Artycles and pointes of the falſe worſhyppynge of God, and falſe Goddes ſeruyce: To thinte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t that ye may<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe, that the controuerſye of theſe dayes is not without great and vrgent cauſes.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Marke well. Rom. 5. i. Pet. 3. He. 9.10. 1. Ioh. 2.</note> Thys faith in Chriſte doth ſurely af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyrme and eſtablyſhe, that Chriſte alone by hys onely oblacion vpon the croſſe, ones made for all, hath made perfect ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſfaction for all the ſynnes of the vny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſall worlde, ſo that nowe there is no newe ſacryfyce or oblacion more for our ſynnes, in the Chriſtianite, nor can be. But onely an offeringe of geuinge ouer
<pb facs="tcp:16295:16"/>
of oure ſelues, a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tryte &amp; penite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t harte, and the prayſe of God, theſe are no ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne offerynges, but thanke offeringes. This teacheth Paule throught out the whole Epyſtle to the hebreues.</p>
            <p>But Chriſte hath left &amp; ordeined vnto his churche, a dayly memoryal or reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braunce of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame onely ſacrifice,<note place="margin">Marke well. The ſup<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>per of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lorde.</note> which is his ſupper, wherin he fedeth and nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſſheth the Chriſtians ſpyrytually with his very body and bloude vnto euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting lyfe, and the Chryſtians receyue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Sacrament of the body and bloude of Chriſte, with thankes and praiſe, for this benefyte, that Chriſte offered his bodye for vs, and ſhed his bloude for the remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of our ſynnes, and geue them ſelues ouer wyllyngly to dye concerninge ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, to mortyfye the olde man, and offer ſacryfyces of thankeſgeuinge, and ſacry<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fyces of prayſe, for al the mercys, which God ſo wonderfully hath ſhewed vs through his ſonne, and one Chriſtian lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth another in dede and trueth, this is the true worſhippinge &amp; ſeruice of God.</p>
            <p>Wherfore it followeth of this,<note place="margin">Of the Maſſe.</note> that it is an errour, and a falſe goddes ſeruice, that men yet wyll vndertake to make a
<pb facs="tcp:16295:17"/>
dayly newe maſſyng ſacryfyce or obla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion, for the ſynnes of the quicke and deade. For this perfect ſatiſfaction; and reconcylyacyon, cometh by the onely ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifyce and oblacion made vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the croſſe where as Chriſte gaue ouer his body, &amp; bare our ſinnes, &amp; ſhed his owne bloude for the remyſſyon of our ſynnes. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the maſſe can in no wyſe be ſuch a ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cryfyce. For it is an horrible errour, that men wyll obtayne and purchace the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſfaction for ſynnes, and the reconcilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of God any other waye than by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> death of Ieſus Chryſte. Yf ſynnes be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaſſed by offerynge of maſſes, than died Chriſte in vayne.</p>
            <p>There is more abhominacion hydden vnder this errour than can be thought &amp; expreſſed. Foraſmuche as the death and paſſyon of Chriſte is our co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forte, by the which, &amp; by nothing elles, we be deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſynne &amp; death, let euery good chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtian iudge in his harte, what a doctrine this is, which ſo lytell regardeth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> death of Chriſte, that ſhe maketh oure workes equall with the death of Chriſte, yea ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcureth and denyeth in a maner all the frutes of the bytter death and paſſyon
<pb facs="tcp:16295:17"/>
of Chriſte. The great &amp; holy appearau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of the maſſe, and the outwarde ſyghte &amp; pompe blyndeth the worlde that ſhe can not ſe the great and abhomynable abuſe. The worde of God dyſcloſeth thys ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>homynacyon, for it teachet one onely ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifyce or oblacion ones offered, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer to be reiterated, which is of perfect ſtrength &amp; power for euer, ſo that this ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cryfyce for ſynne muſte nowe onelye be receyued in faith through the worde and the ſacramente, and we muſt geue than<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes for the ſame with a faithfull harte, knoweledgynge wyth the mouth in lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge and prayſynge his holy name, we muſt alſo geue thankes with the dedes, that we lyfe ſoberly, ryghteouſly, and godly in this lyfe, willyngly and gladly followynge Chriſt, which bought vs w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſuch a great price, of his moſt holy ſacri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fyce vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> croſſe, &amp; purifyed vs for his owne people to him ſelfe, that from hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cefurth we ſhoulde lyue innocently, as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chyldren of God. For God ſaith,<note place="margin">Leui. 19.</note> I am holy, therfore be ye holy alſo. Leui. xix.</p>
            <p>Nowe haue they of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lordes ſupper<note place="margin">The ſup<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>per of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lorde.</note> not only made a newe daily ſinne offri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g for to make dayly ſatiſfaction therby for
<pb facs="tcp:16295:18"/>
ſynne, and to appeaſe goddes ire and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation. But haue alſo wholy chaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged and alterated the teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of Chriſt or his ſupper, for they haue forbidden y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> laye people to receyue the one parte, and they conſtrayne and compell the worlde to receyue the one parte onely which is manyfeſtly againſt the worde and ordy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce of God: For he inſtytuted both kyndes to be receiued of his Chriſtians, Sainct Paule taught and ordayned it ſo to the Corinthia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s.<note place="margin">1. Cor. 11.</note> The primatiue church did vſe it ſo, &amp; the holy Byſſhoppes, Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prian, Auguſtine. &amp;c. kept it ſo. Therfore muſt the pope nedes be in a wrong way ſeynge he hath no commiſſyon nor com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manndement to alter nor to diminiſhe god<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des worde, as alſo Gerſon writeth.</p>
            <p>Nowe do I aſke you on your conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, whether of theſe is mooſt ſure in his conſcience? There are two Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, the one receyueth the ſacrament, accordinge as Chriſte hym ſelfe dyd inſtitute and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>maunde it to be vſed vntyll the laſt day, and as the Apoſtles, the true prymatiue churche, Auguſtine, Cypriane and ſuche lyke haue vſed the ſame, and geueth glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye vnto Chriſte, that he certaynely hath
<pb facs="tcp:16295:18"/>
not erred from his inſtitucion, for noma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> coulde better inſtitute it tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chriſt, nowe this man hath on his ſyde, Chriſte, the worde of God, the Apoſtles, &amp; the whole chriſtianitie, which at that tyme was con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>iected by the Apoſtles, and he hath alſo on his ſyde the mooſt holyeſt and beſt learned fathers.</p>
            <p>The other Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s wyll receyue the ſacramente after the Popes wyll, he ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth not whether God do ſo require it or not, this man hath on his ſyde, Pope in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocente the thyrde, which at Rome in the laterane churche with his counſayll dyd forbydde the holy communyon to be ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to the children, and commaunded y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> layte to receyue but the one parte therof in the yere of oure Lorde, a thouſande two hundreth .xv. Nowe tell me I praye you, which of theſe two Chriſtians ſhall at the laſt daye ſtande in better caſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God, concerninge the ſacrament? The one maye ſaye, I haue done as Gods worde did teache me, then muſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other nedes ſaye that he hath done after the inſtitution of a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Nowe God hath not geuen his worde in vayne, but he wyll that we ſhall followe the ſame. Is
<pb facs="tcp:16295:19"/>
it not than great pitye, that the pope wil compell the poore chriſtianitie to receyue the one part of the communion onely, without Gods worde, yea contrary to the expreſſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundement of god? And ſhal men yet holde their peace &amp; ſaye no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinge to it? No, Sainct Paule doth cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe the Angels if they ſhould preache any other goſpell, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that which he had prea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ched,<note place="margin">Galat. 1. 1. Cor. 15.</note> Galat. 1. Howe come we tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to this that we ſhall ſuffre the pope to burden oure conſcyences, whyche doth peruerie goddes worde and ordynaunce, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſydes that curſeth and deſtroyeth all the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that kepe goddes ordinaunce?</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Marke well.</note>Item, yf the faith in Chryſte doth onely iuſtyfye, and if the fayth of the goſpel doth loke for ſaluacion, of the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re grace and mercy of God, wythout oure deſeruynges, but by the workes and merytes of Chryſte, and yf we do iuſtely confeſſe, that we can not deſerue the ſame, becauſe we are borne ſynners, and although we kept all the commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dementes that yet we are vnprofytable ſeruauntes.<note place="margin">Luce. 17.</note> Luce .xvij. But yf we beleue that Chryſte dyed for vs, and deſerued for vs remyſſyon of ſynnes and euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinge
<pb facs="tcp:16295:19"/>
lyfe, as we haue playnely and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uydently in.<note place="margin">Ro. 4.5. Gala. 3. Ephe. 2. 1. Tim. 2 Hebr. 9. 1. Pet. 2.</note> Saynt Paules Epyſtles to the Romaynes, Galathians, and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſians, &amp;c. that good workes are done of vs of duetie, for the profyte of oure neyghbour, and to the glory of God, So muſt it nedes folowe that all ſuch doctri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes are falſe, as teache vs to do our wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kes to this intent, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> through the ſame we maye extynguyſſhe ſynne, and become good and ryghteous. For theſe two can<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>not ſtande together, to be iuſtifyed by grace through fayth, and to be iuſty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyed by the merytes and deſeruinges of oure workes. Yf it be grace, then is it not oure deſeruing, If it be deſeruing, then is it not grace. And as Paule ſaith,<note place="margin">Gal. 2.</note> Galat. ij. If the ryghteouſnes come by the lawe, that is if mem be made good and ryghteous by the lawe or by wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes, then dyed Chryſte in vayne. But yf he dyed not in vayne,<note place="margin">Rom. 4.</note> but for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myſſyn of oure ſynnes. Roma. iiij. Then muſt it followe neceſſarely,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 15</note> whan the death of Chryſte doth onely make ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction for ſynnes, and the fayth in Chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſte doth onely ſaue and purefye, that the worlde hath ben deceyued by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> doctrine
<pb facs="tcp:16295:20"/>
of workes, as foundinge and inſtituting of monaſteries, orders, pilgrimages, &amp; al relygions and goddes ſeruices inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by man. For by all theſe thinges ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue men intended to ſatyſfye for ſynne to deſerue grace, and to be made good and ryghteous notwithſtandinge that the ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nour of iuſtifycation pertaineth to noma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> but onely to the precious death of Chriſt and the ſhedinge of his bloude. I would fayne ſe his face that durſte be ſo bolde as to denye this truthe. But if this truth ſtandeth and abydeth, then muſt nedes fall down to the grounde, whatſoeuer hytherto hath ben kept and taught to thintent that men thereby ſhoulde be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued and come to God.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Hebr. 5.6.8.9.</note> Item the worthy prieſthode of Chriſt wherin conſyſteth all our conforte, is by the Popes doctrine defaced and diſanul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led.<note place="margin">Gen. 22 Pſa. 101. Hebr. 7.</note> For the ſcripture teacheth vs, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> father by the conuenau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of an othe, hath conſecrated and made his ſonne an euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting pryeſte, which not onely ones by the ſacryfyce of his body hath ſanctifyed his electe,<note place="margin">Ioh. 17. Roma. 3 1. Tim. 2 1. Ioh. 2.</note> but alſo apeareth yet in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſight of God for vs, as a perfecte mediatour and aduocate, a faythfull and mercyfull
<pb facs="tcp:16295:20"/>
biſſhop, in thoſe thinges which we haue to do before God, in whoſe name we muſt call and praye to God, and than God hath promiſed to heare vs.<note place="margin">Hebr. 5.6.7.8.9.</note> All this teacheth vs the Epiſtle to the Hebrewes and other ſcriptures, and they do not ſhewe vs any other mediatour nor aduo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cate before God. Of this it followeth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it is an vnſure, falſe and erronious doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tryne, which the pope and his adheren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes teache, namely that they make Chriſt fearfull as though we muſt haue other mediatours in heauen, to bringe vs fyrſt to Chriſt. Where is here the truſte and confydence in Chriſt?</p>
            <p>Nowe iudge your ſelues I pray you. Do ye thinke yet y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we ſtriue for nought with the Papacye? Is not the matter waighty ynough? It toucheth our ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion, which is god him ſelfe, what thing is there greater? Yf we ſuffre oure ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues to be brought to this beleue, that we muſt and maye by oure owne workes &amp; ſatiſfaction put out ſynnes, deſerue the grace of God, be iuſtifyed and ſaued, then haue we therby denyed the power of the death of Chriſte, and his precious bloude. Tell me then nowe, where to
<pb facs="tcp:16295:21"/>
wyll ye vſe the death &amp; bloude of Chriſt yf it ſhoulde not waſſhe awaye ſynnes puryfye and yuſtyfye vs? Therfore let euery man pondre wyth hym ſelfe in his conſcience, and waye the whole matter, for it is not ſo lyght as men thin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke. Yf we fall from our doctrine of faith then fall we from Chriſte, then haue we no redemer, then haue we no ſacryfyce for our ſynnes, than lyeth ſynne, death, and perpetuall damnation ſtyll vpon vs than is God yet angry and not appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, &amp; there is no grace but mere wrath indignacion,<note place="margin">Hebr. x.</note> and a fearfull lokynge for the iudgement. Hebr. x. For noman ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth to loke for any grace at Goddes ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de without Chriſt, our onely mercy ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te. Thus is Chriſte with his merites ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcured and darkened, yea taken awaye from vs by the popyſtycall doctryne, and oure truſt and confydence tourned to oure owne workes. Howe can we a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byde this?</p>
            <p>Yea ſaye they, but the hier powers wyll not ſuffer this doctrine. Anſwere. I can not tell,<note place="margin">Marke well.</note> I ſuppoſe that they woul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de ſuffre it well ynough, yf it were ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actely opened and declared vnto them.
<pb facs="tcp:16295:21"/>
And although they woulde not abyde it yet may here euery Chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> man thinke that it is expedient for him, to take holde on God, and the trueth, without conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pt of the hyer powers, and in this caſe not to follow y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wordly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t.<note place="margin">Act. 4.5.</note> This doth alſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpirituall or eccleſiaſtical law admytte, for it is written .x. Diſtinc. x. non lycet, It beco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Emperour to pretende any thynge contrary to the lawe of God, nor to do any thinge that is contrary to the rulers of the Euange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lycall, Prophetical or Apoſtolical truth. Item agayne .xi. q. iii. Si dominus. Yf it be euyll which the Emperour co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deth, than anſwere,<note place="margin">Act. 4.5.</note> we muſt obeye God rather then men, but in ſuche thinges as are not contrary to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> commaundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of God, we muſt obeye. More ouer .x. q. iij. Qui reſiſtit. Whan the Emperour com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>maundeth oun thinge &amp; God another. What doth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chriſten ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> iudge? There is God, whiche is of greater power. O Emperour pardon vs here, ye treathen captiuitie, god treateneth hel.<note place="margin">Ephe. 6. 2 Cor. 10 Sapi. 5.</note> Here muſt ye take youre faith as a ſhelde, by the whiche ye maye quenche all the fyery dartes of your enemies.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:16295:22"/>
               <note place="margin">Marke well.</note>Yet ſaye they further. The popiſſhe doctrin is olde, yf ſhe were not true, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> muſt the churche erre. Anſwere. Yf ye be a chriſten man, then beleue ye Chriſte ſtedfaſtely in his wordes of the goſpell, and ye do al ſo take y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame worde for the very true doctryne of God. Nowe if ſhe be ryght and true, then muſt it nedes be falſe, and erronious whatſoeuer is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the ſame, what nede men to care much for the lenght of tyme? The le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ght of tyme, ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not make a falſe thinge true. Yf the ſcripture therfore be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> true waye then muſt he nedes erre that forſaketh y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame waye, and walketh an other way, whether he be great or ſmall, many or fe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>we, holy or ſynners.</p>
            <p>Yet ſaye they moreouer. That theſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re the laſt dayes, in the whiche we ought to beware of falſe Prophetes. What &amp; yf the luterians (for ſo do they call vs) were the ſame falſe Prophetes? Anſwer Serche the ſcripture,<note place="margin">Iohn. 5.</note> and iudge hardely, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ye hitte, let him be hitted. The ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſayth,<note place="margin">1. Tim. 4 2. Tim. 3 2. Pet. 3 Iudi. 1. 2. Teſſ. 2</note> that the falſe Prophetes of the later dayes ſhall forbydde matry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monye, and meates whyche God hath created, they ſhall denye Chriſte that
<pb facs="tcp:16295:22"/>
bought them, that is they ſhall denye y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame beinge, they ſhall haue a ſhyne or a colloer of godlynes, but they ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye the power therof.<note place="margin">Marke well.</note> Yf ye fynde theſe tokens in the Lutherians (as ye call the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) then take them for falſe Propetes. But if ye fynde them not by them, than loke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boute you, and ye ſhall ſoone perceyue, who erreth. Wherfore do the Lutheria<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s (as ye call them) ſuffre ſo muche ſclaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deringe and perſecution. Euen for this cauſe,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 7. Hebr. 13.</note> that they wil haue matrimony fre and at lybertie, euen as it is fre for euery man in the worde of God. They wyll y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> for meates ſake no mans conſcience ſhall be burdened, ſo that they geue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> honoure onely to Chriſt, that he through his paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion hath bought vs out of euerlaſtinge death, and that he puryfyeth vs all fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſynne by his bloude. Therfore do they reiecte the maſſynge ſacrifyce, &amp; whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uer is done to that intent, that therby me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wyll be deliuered from ſinne and death. They are alſo reuyled, becauſe they lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de a commune ſimple lyfe in the ſtate of wedloke, as an honeſt laye man, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any ſhyne of a pryuate holines with out ſhauen crounes, graye amyſes, ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plices,
<pb facs="tcp:16295:23"/>
ſtoles, and ſuch lyke abilleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, for the whiche thinges ſake, the eſtate of prieſthode hither to in the worlde hath be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> counted as holy, &amp; contrary wyſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſtate of layemen, as vnholye and prophane.</p>
            <p>For the ſpirituall fathers, haue drawe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to them ſelues &amp; appropriated to them ſel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ues the Chriſtian offyces, wherby their eſtate hath ben counted the State of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection and holynes and the State of the laytie hath ben counted heathen and pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>phane, for they woulde offer alone to God, as the prieſtes in the olde teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t offered for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people. They haue eſtemed their prayer of greater valoure a great deale, then the prayer of the leaye men: And yet it is but bought, ſolde, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled gere, which for the mooſt parte is done wythout faith and earneſt zeale, without ſpirite and trueth, for moneys and legacyes ſake. For yf there were neyther money nor ſubſtaunce, the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſteryes, chauntryes and churches ſhoulde ſone be ſtyll without prayenge, ſyngynge and maſſynge. They haue kept the whole ſacrament to them ſelues and geuen vs the one halfe. And of theſe
<pb facs="tcp:16295:23"/>
their manyfolde errours and erronious occupyenges, haue they made no iuſte accompte as yet, but haue onely alleged the ſcrypture in a wronge ſence, and the inſtitucion of popes &amp; counſeyls, whiche neuertheles they haue not kept them ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues as I can eaſely proue.</p>
            <p>The fourth counſayll of Charthagen commaundeth that a byſſhoppe ſhall ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue a ſmall poore houſe, decking, and lod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginge, and a poore table and lyuynge, and that he ſhall ſeke the reſpecte of his dignitie, by fayth and deſeruing of his lyfe. Where do they here kepe theyr counſayll? Thinke ye that nowe there coulde not be founde a byſſhoppe, which beſydes his Iewells and plate, were of as great or greater abilitie, than a te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral Prince? Yes truly, I am ſure of it.</p>
            <p>The .xx Canon of the forſaide coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayll commaunded, that a biſſhoppe ſhal auoyde temporall eares, &amp; do nothing el<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>les but reade praye ſtudye and preache. Where is there one that doth this? Or yf they counte it ſo ſmale a matter not to kepe the counſayles, why do they tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> make the tranſgreſſyons of the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les ſo greuous vnto vs?</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:16295:24"/>The .xiiij. Canon Concily Neoceſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rienſis wyll that there ſhall be no more but ſeuen Deacons in a great citie. Whe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re haue they kept this? Where as nowe is a ſmall towne there are .x. or .xx. prie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes, where as the Chapelaynes as Dea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cons ſhoulde be for the poore as in the Apoſtles tyme,<note place="margin">Actu. 6. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Tim. 3</note> and the Curate ſhoulde preache. Of the other ſurte do we not ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de half ſo many.</p>
            <p>Euen in this counſayll it is comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, that whan a prieſte taketh a wyfe, he ſhall be prieſte no longer. This haue they weakened goodly, although they do neyther kepe the ſame alſo, for they punyſſhe it by death. But this counſayll doth onely depoſe them from theyr offyce.</p>
            <p>The fyrſte canon of the fourth coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayll of carthagyne commaunded, that noman ſhall be ordayned and made a byſſhop, except he be examyned before and founde to be well learned and exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyſed in the holy ſcrypture, ſober, dyſcre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te, and mercyfull. Howe many are there founde nowe that can the Cateciſmus? Thus do they inſtitute and commaunde many thynges, and yet they kepe them
<pb facs="tcp:16295:24"/>
not them ſelues.</p>
            <p>The .vi. Canon amonge them that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re called Canones Apoſtoles, ſayth, A byſſhop or prieſt ſhall in nowyſe put a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waye from him his wedded wyfe for re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lygions ſake. But yf he put her awaye from hym, he ſhall be excommunicated, and yf he ſo continue, he ſhal be depoſed. Nowe haue they concluded of late, that whoſoeuer putteth not awaye his wyfe from him ſhall not be ſuffered.</p>
            <p>The .vii. Canon of the Apoſtles, Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons commaundeth that a byſſhop, prie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſte, or Deacon, ſhall in no wyſe addicte hym ſelfe in worldely matters or cares, or yf he do it, he ſhall be depoſed. They that haue ben at Auſburgh at the conuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation there, haue ſeene ryghtwell who woulde put hym ſelfe euen in the myd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of all the buſynes. But here are they mercyfull vnto them ſelues, and they ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſoone diſpenſe therin. But yf a yonge prieſte to auoyde offence marieth a wyfe there is the fyre prepared, and leſſe mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy than in hell.</p>
            <p>The fourth Canon Concely Gangie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſis ſayth, whoſoeuer maketh any dyffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of a maryed prieſte, for wedlockes
<pb facs="tcp:16295:25"/>
ſake, as though for wedlockes ſake he myght not offer or ſaye maſſe, or who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer therfore doth with drawe hym ſelfe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his maſſe, accurſed be he. Nowe wil they not heare ſpeakinge of wedloc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke, but ſtyrre vp Princes and Lordes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt vs, and can in the meane ſeaſon goodly defende there vnchaſtelyfe.</p>
            <p>Item Diſt. lxxxi. c. Si qui preſbiteri forbyddeth the ſpiritual lawe to all prie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes and deacons, beynge whoremon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers or fornicatours, to entre into the churche ſayenge on this wyſe, what prie<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtes Deacons or Subdeaco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ſoeuer they be that liue in vncle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>lines or whoredome, to them we forbydde in the name of our almyghtie God, and by the power and vertue of ſayncte Peter, the intraunce into the churche vntill they amende their lyfe. But yf they wyll contynue in their ſynne, then ſhall none of you heare their offyce, for their bleſſynge is tourned into a curſe, and their prayer into ſinne. And whoſoeuer wyll not obeye this holſome co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundement, ſhall fal into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſynne of Idolatrye. This canon did Pope Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory write vnto all Italians &amp; Dout<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chemen.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:16295:25"/>Who is there nowe amonge the ſpy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritualtie that regardeth this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? I haue thought it good to ſhewe you a lyttell for an introduction, howe the ſpiritualtie kepe not their own lawes euen were as they are beſte And becauſe the Emperours, Kinges and Princes ceaſe not cryenge, Canons, fathers, cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayls, onely becauſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vnlearned ſhould thinke their matter to be good notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandinge that it is euyll and wicked, &amp; that they might teache and lyue not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly contrary to gods worde, but alſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to their owne lawes. And yet wyl they blynde the worlde wyth open eyes, and make them to beleue that they haue ruled well.</p>
            <p>But howe is it with mannes inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions are they all to be deſpyſed, than wyll ther followe a madde and diſſolute lyuinge? Anſwer. Yf the curates dyd ſo ſore plye goddes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundement as they do mennes inſtitucions, there woulde followe no madde and diſſolute liuinge. But to thintent that ye maye knowe the grounde of the matter, thus it ſtandeth with mennes inſtitutions, they are of many ſortes.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:16295:26"/>
               <note place="margin">Sap. 6. Pro. 20. and .24. Rom. 13. Tim. 3. 1 Pet. 2.</note>Fyrſt, we ſpeake not here of ordinau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces and inſtitucions of the hier powers, for they go ouer body and goodes, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concerninge the temporall lyfe, and they ought to be kept peaceably, whan they be not againſt God. Rom. i. b. i. Pet. ij.</p>
            <p>Secondarely the diſputacion is of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> inſtitucions that haue ben made in the churche for goddes ſeruice, or ſuche as are concerninge ſpyrytuall perſons (as they are called) or goddes ſeruice. Here do we teache by the foundations of god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des worde, that the conſciences muſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nely be taught &amp; ledde by goddes worde and not with mannes tradicio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, for this concerneth ſaluation or damnacion. Here ought he onely to commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de and to ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue a do,<note place="margin">2. pa. 20. Mat. 10 Luc. 12.</note> that hath power to condemne or to ſaue body and ſoule. Therfore all ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s inſtitucions that are made contrary to the worde of God, as the forbiddinge of matrymony. &amp;c. ſhall be in the conſcience of leſſe then of no repentation. Alſo wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mennes inſtitutions are made or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded to this intent, that therby gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce maye be obtayned, God worſhipped, and men ſaued lyke as men are forced and compelled to certayne faſtinge da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yes
<pb facs="tcp:16295:26"/>
crepyng to the croſſe proceſſyons, forbyddinge of meates, or howe ſoeuer they be called, they ſhall be regarded of a chriſten man leſſe then nothinge, and they can not bynde the conſciences. For the chriſtian lybertye is not onely of po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, that we are delyuered from ſynne and the power of the deuyll by Chriſte, but alſo that Moſes ceremonies and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther eccleſiaſtical ordinaunces, of dayes, meates, and of ſuche lyke do not bynde vs, yf they be kept, men are not ſaued by them, yf they be tranſgreſſed without ar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rogauncye and offence, me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> committe no deadly ſynne. But whan the biſſhoppes make any inſtitutions without burde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninge of mens conſciences, for a decent order, whether it be holy dayes or other thinges, to thintent that al thinges in the chriſtianite maye he done after a comly ſorte and a decent order, not that it be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to ſaluacion, the ſame wyll we kepe gladly, and teache that they ſhal be kept. All this is grounded. Eſaye. xxix. Mat. xv. xxiij. Colo. ij. i. Timo. vi. Rom. xvi. Galat. i. iiij. Tit. i.</p>
            <p>This did alſo Auguſtine teach aboue a thouſande yeres a go in the Epiſtle to
<pb facs="tcp:16295:27"/>
Ianuarius. It is no newe thinge, but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ryght olde catholyke doctrine. For the Prophetes Chriſt, and the Apoſtles are older then the pope &amp; the eccleſiaſticals inſtitucions and conſayles. Wherfore I beſeche and exhorte you by the glorious comming of Ieſus Chriſte at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> laſt day,<note place="margin">Mat. 25</note> that ye wil ſhewe vnto this great entre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe this fauour, whiche was wont to be ſhewed to a ſmall worldely entrepri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe, that is, that ye be not to ſwifte in iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gement. But that ye wyll fyrſt by your ſelfe earneſtly with a prayer vnto God through Chriſte, for the ſpirite of trueth, perpende and pondre the matter and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwarde iudge. And I beſeche you ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke in worth this ſmall inſtruction wryt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in haſte, for I ſeke nothinge elles but that our faithfull God and Lorde Ieſus Chriſte, may be exactely knowen of you and of many men to their righteouſnes and ſaluacion: which voucheſafe to ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de vs his ſpirite, and to make vs true chriſtians. Amen. Salute all them that are with you, and reioyce with vs of the aboundau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t grace of God through Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſte, as of our onely conforte Amen.</p>
            <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <pb facs="tcp:16295:27"/>
            <q>¶ Seke peace, and enſue it.
<bibl>Pſalm. xxxiij. i. Pet. iij.</bibl>
            </q>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's device of Walter Lynne</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <q>
               <bibl>Pſal. cxj. b. Prou. ix. b. Iob. xxviij. c. Eccle. i. c.</bibl>
The fear of the Lorde is the begyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninge of wyſedome.</q>
            <p>¶Imprinted by me Gwalter Lynne, dwellyng vpon So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers kaye, by Byllynges gate. In the yeare of our Lorde God. M.D.Xlviij.</p>
            <p>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> 
               <hi>Cum gratia &amp; priuilegio ad im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>primendum ſolum.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:16295:28" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:16295:28"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
